[Music]
welcome back to the sense making series
this film is going to be about
conspiracy and spirituality
but really it's kind of about the
balance between certainty and
uncertainty and the dance between them
which i think is core
to sense making so i'm going to unpack
what for me feels like quite a new
phenomenon or at least has really ramped
up massively since the beginning of the
pandemic
and that's this sort of mashup between
conspiracy communities and spiritual
communities which a lot of
other people have also commented on so
we're going to hear from friends of the
channel like jamie wheel
and some other new voices i'm going to
be looking back at some of the really
big moments over the last couple of
months
including the runaway success of the
pandemic
trailer which was kind of everywhere a
couple of months ago and has got a
really really interesting backstory
and also i'm going to talk a little bit
about the david ike interviews on london
reel
which we might have covered a couple of
times before on this channel as well
and want to give a disclaimer right at
the beginning that
it's very tricky to talk about
conspiracy at all
and we're really i'm really looking at
it through the focus of sense
making i'm not looking at the truth
content or otherwise or most of the kind
of conspiracy narratives
that's what you're interested in there's
plenty of other places you can get that
from
but i'm also trying to fill a little bit
of a gap because i feel like
the traditional media or the mainstream
media has a bit of a blind spot around a
lot of these topics
because they don't really they've got a
very sort of secular and rationalist
bias
so don't really understand spirituality
so
first i'm going to unpack what i think
is quite a new phenomenon
so everyone's kind of familiar with the
old school infowars alex jones
kind of conspiracy as entertainment
raging against the globalists
i don't like them putting chemicals in
the water that turn the freaking frogs
gay
but both the david ike interview and the
pandemic film are kind of different they
come from a different place
so in the david ike interview on london
real we had sort of veering between the
conscious
and spiritual when we realized the true
nature of what we are which is
consciousness
eternal exploring forever consciousness
having a brief experience called human
to the kind of really dark and paranoid
i have
tracked this these people this cult
for 30 years full-time and i've seen
their
staggering shocking levels of
psychopathy
and the back story for the film pandemic
is really interesting as well because
the director mickey willis
used to make films about kind of
spiritual concepts like the secret
and then the film pandemic took a very
different tone because if we don't stop
this now
we can not only forget our republic and
our freedom but we can forget humanity
because
we'll be killed by this agenda and an
analysis
after pandemic was released showed that
it spread equally through kind of what
you
might have assumed was kind of quite
left-wing natural health
new age circles and then quite
right-wing
q and on conspiratorial circles
and the movie spread like wildfire
through the spiritual community
which i think is a phenomenon that's
really worth unpacking not looking at
the content of the films not looking at
the content of the interviews
but what we're seeing is a wider
phenomenon and i don't think you can
really do this without understanding
some of the nature of spirituality and
some of the nature of like genuine
spiritual awakening
and i think the problem that we get with
the mainstream
when they kind of look at this stuff and
they debunk it or they kind of just
assume it's bogus is that they don't
really have a frame of reference because
they don't really understand
spirituality
that's what i really want to unpack in
this film and
i think it can only really be explained
when we understand what genuine
spiritual awakening means
and how that process can also become
uh very difficult to navigate very
difficult to make sense of
and i caught up with a friend of the
channel jamie wheel
who wrote the book stealing fire which
was probably the the best guide to
transformational culture
and awakening that's come out and he had
a really interesting take on it
so anything that creates a boundary
dissolving
self-eroding narrative collapsing lived
experience
is then prone to well now that's all
been blown to smithereens
what do i repopulate it with so a lot of
people go from oh i was all up in my
head
i was chasing you know the nine to five
and a gold watch or my 401k
i realized that was just all a fucking
illusion so
now i believe in aliens and angels and
my ability to manifest stuff
and oh by the way if that's true then
maybe vaccines
aren't true maybe the who maybe bill
gates maybe maybe maybe
and you end up kind of just going
through the floorboards
of logical consistent sense making
into if what i've been sold
to start with was a bill of goods i am
now
credibly willing to believe damn near
anything
as a replacement versus realizing that
reconstructing a more complex subtle
nuance post-conventional reality is
actually 10 times
more work so i'm going to start by
saying i know it's really difficult to
talk about conspiracy theory full stop
it's what is often called an overloaded
term in that it refers to a lot of
different things
and it can often be used to dismiss
anything that's not a mainstream
narrative
um and i think i'd be interested
actually
if people can come up with some ways of
differentiating because it feels very
different to me
like alternative histories corruption
collusion
conspiracy and a really good example of
that was the recent interview with tom
o'neill on the joe rogan experience
looking at the manson killings looking
at the jfk assassination
and building a really compelling and
really interesting
uh alternative history that seems like
for me really rings true really
it really seems to explain a lot of what
was going on in the 60s
um but then there's a qualitative
difference like something that feels
very different
and that's an all-encompassing
explanation for the world
and where people attach a real sort of
deep level of certainty to it as well
and i was kind of i i've not been able
to really
find anyone who's being able to identify
the difference between those two things
but they feel very
qualitatively different a friend of mine
ivan
actually put up something recently i
think came closest to explaining what
the difference was
and he talked about it in terms of
archetypes he's got a background with
the psychologist jung and looks at
young's way of
uh understanding the world which is
archetypes and the sort of mythical
dimension
and he said that what
the difference is when we're in
relationship to reality or when we're
in relationship to something that feels
like an archetypal force
where all of the power and all the
agency is outside oneself
rather than it being us feeling that we
have power and we have agency
and there's a real difference between
that being aware of when we're in
relationship to something that feels
that it has all of the power and we have
none
we need to be really careful because
that's obviously a very disempowering
place to be and
there's almost uh if we feel that we're
in relationship to something like that
it almost has an archetypal dimension or
a religious dimension to it
i've seen that there is there is a
tendency for people that plunge
too far into this narrative or this
alternative sense making paradigm is
that they start slipping from reality
bit by bit
and they sort of fall into these dark
all-encompassing dreamscapes that feel
almost trance-like
so this channel is mostly a focus on how
we make sense of the world
sense-making the crisis in sense-making
because
that seems to be the the main
problem right now how we find truth
together in this very uncertain time
very uncertain world
and i think one of the things is a
realization that we have to be really
aware of ourselves of our inner world of
how we're attaching and how we're
attaching more certainty for example to
things than
the inputs or the evidence would warrant
which is something that daniel
schmacktenberger talked about in the war
on sense making film we put out
how do i make sense of what is true and
what isn't true
about signal coming in and then how do i
parse from lots of signal what might be
true about reality
almost no one who has fervent ideas has
a good epistemic basis
for the level of certainty they hold
there's a decoupling between how much
certainty they have and how much
certainty they
should have through right process so i'm
specifically talking about these
all-encompassing
conspiracy theories here which is why
i'm going to talk about david ike
because david ike
really epitomizes that the level of
certainty that he brings
for example in the london real interview
where he's talking about the virus as a
hoax
and this uh kovid 19
scam hoax has been designed
to create in
very fast time the very
global centralization of power that um
that we have or i have been um
highlighting for 30 years was coming and
i also think that there's a reason why
a lot of these explanations are really
resonating with people is because
i think a lot of them are largely
picking up on a right intuition about
the world
i think we're in as we've said in many
of the other films we're in a system
that is failing
massively that is really out on many
levels and i think
what a lot of these conspiracy theories
do is they
collapse what should be an ongoing
inquiry process
into what's really going on into a
concrete uh
narrative good guys bad guys and
what becomes kind of an ideology and
that i want to really unpack like what
what do they get right and what do they
get wrong which i'll come back to at the
end of the film
why i'm so interested in this topic why
i'm so passionate about it is i think
that
as a culture we're going to have to
start really grappling with what it
means to have a spiritual experience
because more and more people are having
them in some of the latest surveys they
found that more than 50 percent of
people have had some kind of religious
or spiritual experience
so understanding what the benefits are
what the pitfalls are
is hugely important and also the
psychologist stanislav groff
talked about psychedelics and other
experiences as being non-specific
amplifiers
that they basically made everything in
our in our world in our lives
more intense and what we're going
through right now with the pandemic
is kind of a non-specific amplifier
like it's making everything much more
intense for all of us we're all focused
on the same thing
and i think we're going to have to
understand we're going to have to
really integrate this understanding of
spiritual experience and also the
concept of spiritual emergency which is
another concept of stan grafts
and a friend of mine jules evans and tim
reed have just brought out a book
about spiritual emergency and we're
going to hear from them a little bit
later on
so i'm going to talk about david ike
because i think it's a perfect example
of
a genuine spiritual experience and then
what can happen
if we try and make sense of it
prematurely he's seen as a fringe figure
by many people
but the first thing to note is that
david ike is actually really really
popular
his interviews on london real before the
pandemic were some of the most popular
films they'd ever put out
and he talks to huge audiences all
around the uk and around the world
david ike so he famously declared
himself the son of god
on the chat show wogan in 1991
and declared that the world was going to
end that year i'm saying that these
things are going to happen
this year then we'll see won't we
and what'll happen if they don't happen
what will happen to you
they will happen because if they don't
happen there will be
no earth and it is as simple as that and
i frankly don't care
what anyone thinks they have free will
to make their own choices on what is
said
i say wait and see now personally
i now look back and i think it's a very
ethically dubious
decision to invite him onto that show in
the middle of an experience like that it
obviously made him a laughing stock and
uh he now talks about how it's pretty
much all anyone remembers about him
let me get this story right the press
claim
that you claim to be the son of god
is that true yes you see the thing is
that
it's quite it's quite funny really you
know 2 000 years ago
had a guy called jesus sat here and said
these same things you would still be
laughing it's really
really funny that we've not really moved
on that much and i've not
shared this publicly before but i've had
similar experiences
of what i would call spiritual emergency
where it feels like
you're at the center of this kind of
huge drama this huge cosmic drama and it
all feels focused on you
and i think that's something that we're
all capable of that we can all go into
at different times
and it's really hard to keep grounded in
the middle of that kind of experience
i was actually looking at making a
documentary about exactly this topic the
relationship between spirituality
mental health i called it learning to
swim
and the reason it was called that is
from a quote by joseph campbell
where he said that the mystic swims in
the same water that the psychotic drowns
and i think that's a really important
realization or insight
so when i went through that experience
it was a hugely intense time i was lucky
enough to have friends and colleagues
who helped me out
but people at work knew about it and
still to this day i'm kind of
embarrassed that people at work know
that i kind of lost it
for a bit and to know that a lot of
people i respect a lot of people i work
with kind of know
this about me i have no idea what it
might be like for someone to go on a
national chat show
during one of those experiences and then
for that to be the main thing that
people remember about them
this is also a really difficult thing to
talk about because you also don't want
to end up saying that all
mental health crises are spiritual
emergencies because
that's also an oversimplification you've
got to be really careful
um and like people have experiences
some people need to be on on drugs to
stabilize them
others don't so i thought the the best
way to talk about this
with kind of responsibility would be to
talk to
tim reed so tim reed is a psychiatrist
he's worked at the sharp end of mental
health in the uk for about 20 years
but he was also studying with stan groff
training as a holotropic breath worker
and really looking into spiritual
emergencies and
he's just brought out this book with
jules evans about spiritual emergency
so i thought he would be the best person
to speak to about the nature of these
experiences
and how he's helped people through them
in the past
as as we go into the deeper parts of the
psyche we might feel
um a combination of of
of spiritual awakening if you like but
also feel drawn into
a closer encounter with with with
aspects of our shadow
by shadow we generally mean those parts
of ourselves
um our individual psyche maybe even our
collective psyche
that we're not aware of that we're blind
to that we can't we can't really see or
hear
um the parts of the psyche that have
maybe been been very wounded
um in our development and we've
constructed often quite elaborate
psychological defenses around them
so when we get to these parts of our
cycle we not only come in
contact with some of the pain that we
hold in these wounds
often the shame but we also
also come into contact with the the
defensive structures that we've
we've built around them so
in any in any deep inner state um it's
really important to to look inside and
to try to figure out something about
these wounds the pain the difficult
emotional space
but that that we but we feel around it
and the defenses so it's a real it's a
real it's real journey inwards
um sometimes people
don't take the attention inwards but
they project everything on to get
onto the outside world there's a term
for that which is often used called a
confusion of levels
that essentially what is an inner
experience that should be taken mostly
symbolically
is unprojected onto the outside worlds
so that
everything is seen out there rather than
rather than
in here but after such experiences
people
people feel so um by very vulnerable
their ego structures if you like have
been cracked
right open um
and in a way they can be likened to um
an infant state and a newborn babies
they need very gentle holding very
gentle space
uh well while they recover themselves
make sense of our experience
and emerge from it and if that doesn't
happen
um if if people
re-engage with ordinary everyday noisy
smelly dirty reality to too quickly it
can be absolutely brutalizing and
this this is very often where we
um we see people running into problems
so coming back to david ike my sense is
that he had a genuine spiritual
experience
but the decision to bring him on to
wogan in the middle of that meant that
it couldn't really complete
in a natural way and as he says turned
him into a laughingstock
but just let just let me just let me say
this they're laughing at you
they're not laughing with you
and i think it's fair to say that he's
still deeply affected by that experience
i've been saying this for so long oh
you're mad that debbie looks mad oh yeah
okay
you're not laughing now are you so as i
said earlier i think that a lot of these
conspiracy theories have
uh traction because they're picking up
on a right intuition
and i think that's a really interesting
frame and i think a lot of the
conspiracy
narratives are picking up that we're in
a deeply
corrupt sick and failing system but what
they do is collapse around a certain
narrative
rather than keeping it as an open
inquiry into what's really going on
and i think we've touched on a lot of
these topics in in previous films
eric weinstein talking about kind of
institutional decay
we have effectively entered a period in
which we cannot trust our
experts we've got two generations of
institutional experts that are corrupted
and that we cannot wake up from this
crazy fever dream that we're all in
because we can't figure out who we can
still trust
the doctors are compromised the
professors are compromised the
journalists are compromised the
politicians are compromised
about the only thing that isn't badly
compromised
are people with an independent source of
sustenance
daniel schmacktenberger talking about
self-terminating systems
rival risk dynamics multiplied by
exponential tech
self-terminate exponential tech is
inexorable we cannot put it away
so we either figure out anti-rivalry or
we go extinct
the human experiment comes to a
completion and that's not to say that
there are not actual conspiracies out
there we've also put out films about the
epstein case
uh the epstein case as you you'll see if
you have a look at that one with with
eric weinstein
looks to me like there's a lot more than
we've been told
and it could kind of link into security
services
and some kind of large structure as eric
talks about
the really difficult part of the story
david is is that almost certainly we're
talking about some kind
of operation that was being run
with knowledge of governments that may
have involved
pedophilia and was not shut down and in
a way i think it's
almost impossible to go through this
experience of questioning our given
reality
and not pop into uh some kind of
questioning of the entire consensus
reality but it's really important not to
get stuck
in those fixed narratives on the other
side we've talked on the channel about
the key things that we need to learn to
deal with this
shift that we're all going through is
discernment and improving our sense
making really improving
the way that we make sense of the world
so it's interesting to look at pandemic
through this lens as well
and the director mickey willis so mickey
willis as company it's called elevate
films
and he used to make sort of spiritually
inspiring content
uh including a film about the secret the
secret being about kind of manifestation
and that
if you set your visualizations the world
will kind of
align itself towards you and i'd also
put him
sort of firmly on the left of the
political spectrum on the woke side
he had this very famous viral hit where
he took his son to the toy store
and got him a doll azai here had a
birthday recently and
he received two presents that were
exactly the same so i said let's go to
the toy store and we'll exchange one for
something that you don't have
and this is what he chose
now how do you think a dad feels when
his son
wants to get this
yeah yeah
you say yeah choose it choose your
expression
choose what you're into choose your
sexuality choose whatever and you have
my promise right now both of you
to love you and accept you no matter
what
life you choose yeah
and actually jamie wheel who we heard
from earlier in the film also knows
mickey from before
interestingly um the film pandemic which
actually
came from folks who are familiar with
elevate films and mickey willis um
in the last year or so he has taken a an
abrupt a
very noticeable uh more
conspiratorial and kind of right-leaning
turn
where he used to be in the kind of
conchi new age space and very you know
doing
documentaries on ayahuasca i think
earlier doing something about the secret
so very much kind of new thought
positivity and kind of pro-social in
fact i think he had another viral video
where he was
in the car with his son you know talking
about hey it's okay for my son to play
with a little mermaid doll
so very much on the kind of you know
secular progressive left
more or less with this new film that
he's come out with which is
anti-vaxx you know elevating a lot of
those old stories dusting them off and
repackaging them
into the corona you know million
the propagation of that was
overwhelmingly far right so the
center of the word cloud cluster for the
network map of how that went it was
qanon
and then a whole lot of kind of bright
body and other things so
so what is going on there and whether
that was deliberate and intentional and
that was a specific pre-launch campaign
for it to support it going viral or
whether that was just
memetic stickiness and for whom did that
belt hole
you know and and reached we had prompt
retweets i don't know
but i do know that you know mickey did
not fall off the media turnip truck
yesterday
um so so were there some intentional
um track laying ahead of time it would
make sense i mean anytime you invest in
a project you want people to see it but
for sure
it caught but then pandemic was a very
different tone and a very different film
i won't go too much into the content in
it but as a filmmaker i found
that it had it was a kind of hodgepodge
of lots of different conspiracy theories
it wasn't
really a single narrative which i think
helped it go viral so it was taken up by
people on the left who are kind of
concerned about vaccines and concerned
about natural health
and it was also taken up by people on
the right who are concerned about gate
and concerned about fouchy
and as the the map of the spread of it
showed
it really took off in both of those
areas from queue and on all the way to
natural news and natural health
and that in itself is a really
fascinating phenomenon that we're seeing
these two things coming together
um and i think the best frame that i
have for understanding it is something
that my friend jules evans said recently
so jules brought out the book on
spiritual emergency with tim reed
and was talked about how these two
things like the secret
this sort of the universe is aligned
everything is kind of as i
as i intend and the universe will
conspire to help me
and the alternative of there are these
powers
uh there are these conspiracies that
have all the agency and i have none
that these things can flip together very
easily
one is a kind of positive conspiracy
which you could define by a kind of sort
of mystical experience
like everything is connected
i am connected to everything in the
universe
and that's wonderful the universe's
mission is flowing through me i am
naturally attracting helpers
to to kind of bring this new
age this glorious new age for humanity
into existence
um so you see lots of people in the
occult
in this kind of ecstatic globalism i
call it people like
um h.g wells or like theosophists
or um you know in the in the new age
movement in the 70s and 80s there was a
book by marilyn ferguson called the
aquarium conspiracy
uh h.g wells wrote a book called the
open conspiracy and
these were like ecstatic networked
globalist
progressive free love people
and they're like this is happening an
age of love is happening it's happening
through us we are the
we are the kind of vanguard we are the
elites
okay so that's one what i call a
positive conspiracy
and then there's the negative conspiracy
which kind of grew up
in reaction to that and the negative
it's kind of like the bad trip version
of that
good trip and it's like everything is
connected
um there's an elite controlling
everything but i'm not included
i'm an outsider to it so instead
everything is connected and controlled
by some shadowy elite
of self-appointed kind of masters
uh and and and and they're all kind of
networked together
in their own like think tanks and
organizations and they're controlling
everything and they must be stopped
so david ike for me is a real example of
a kind of arrested development
and my experience and making sense of
what happened to me
is that we have these really huge
spiritual experiences that our egos our
sort of small personalities try and grab
onto and make it personal make it about
us
believe that we have a unique level of
consciousness that we have a unique
ability that we are special as
david ike said in the interview on
london real
i am more powerful than they
are and they freaking
know it i ain't come here
to fail and i frickin won't
why are you more powerful than they are
david why
because i have levels of consciousness
and everybody watching this program has
those same levels of consciousness if
they will only open their minds to it
and this is what the psychologist carl
jung warned specifically about if we're
going to go into these realms
is confusing ourselves our egos with
what he called
the self with a capital s the collective
unconscious the archetypes
that which is much vaster than we are
that we can have glimpses of
and be inspired by but never confuse
ourselves with
because what comes up in that elevated
state and especially afterwards
is all of the stuff that we haven't
dealt with as
we talked about the non-specific
amplifier amplifies all of those other
parts of our personalities
and narcissism and need for approval all
of that comes up and then has to be
dealt with
and if we don't deal with it it will
take us down at some point
and one of the other things to be really
careful of is
instead of integrating and realizing our
own shadow
as jordan peterson so beautifully talked
about the roots of the shadow go all the
way down to hell and we really need to
confront it in ourselves
before we try and tackle it out in the
world jung didn't believe that you could
be a good person until you realized your
capacity for evil i don't mean acted it
out in the world but understand that
it's
possible it's a horrible thing to
realize that you're human
and what being human means like angel
like christ to satan that's the human
being
and that requires honesty that requires
time that requires doing the work
in relationship with others and really
looking at ourselves
and the danger if we don't do that is
that we project all of the stuff that we
haven't looked at and we haven't
examined
out onto the world as tim reed talks
about
it's just really important to do your
own deep inner work
in a meaningful way so you you really
engage with
with shadow and again shadow being those
parts of yourself that you don't really
want to think of think about
the deep wounds the defenses you put up
against them um and if you don't
if you don't engage with shadow this
this tends to be
the result that shadow tends to be
projected
on to get its own environment which can
then become threatening
and the other thing that i would suggest
is that these all-encompassing
conspiracy narratives
are essentially religious in structure
at the heart of it it's very christian
there is a community of the elect
there's a community of the damned there
are the evil ones there are the saved
and even though at some times they seem
really dark
they're actually rapture ideologies
they're utopian because if only we could
expose this group
particular group of people whoever they
are then humanity would be free and
utopia would be at hand
all i can say to that is if only it was
that simple
that's all i got see you soon
rebel wisdom was set up to make sense of
the world at a deeper level than the
mainstream media
it was built for these times of crisis
and change
which is why we want to do what we can
to meet the challenge of the times
more films and also for our rebel wisdom
members
weekly sense making calls with our
amazing interviewees
and also we're introducing the wisdom
gym
a place to practice some of the skills
that we've talked about on the channel
thanks for watching and see you soon